<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vertical_slice_guidelines version="4.3" base="true">

    <!-- ================================================================
    VSA 4.3 — Solo-Agent Base Rules
    Context: 1 human + 1 AI agent | 20–50K LOC | No backward compat
    Priority: Highest. Treat every rule as a compiler error.
    Violations of blocker-severity rules MUST be refused.
    State the rule ID. Propose a compliant alternative.
    ================================================================ -->

    <metadata>
        <n>Vertical Slice Architecture — Solo-Agent AI Base Guidelines</n>
        <version>4.3</version>
        <created>2026-03-17</created>
        <revised>2026-04-16</revised>
        <supersedes>4.2</supersedes>
        <priority>Highest</priority>
        <revision_notes>
            4.3 rev1: CTX-002 replaced — Chunked Refactoring Protocol removed.
            Replaced with Atomic Full-Scope Execution: multi-file changes execute completely
            in one response. Schema changes remain a hard gate. RT-001 through RT-005 updated
            from halt-and-confirm to flag-and-proceed inline, consistent with current agent
            context capacity. /abstract command gate in RT-005 preserved by design.
        </revision_notes>
    </metadata>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 1 — TERMINOLOGY
    ================================================================ -->
    <terminology>
        <term name="Slice">One business capability owning its own entry point, logic, and data. Zero runtime dependency on other Slices.</term>
        <term name="Feature Folder">The physical directory for a Slice. ALL files for that capability live here. No exceptions.</term>
        <term name="Shared Kernel">Infrastructure adapters and pure domain utilities. ZERO business logic permitted.</term>
        <term name="Integration Event">Immutable fact emitted by a Slice after a state change. Consumed asynchronously. Describes what happened, not what to do next.</term>
        <term name="Public Read Model">A read-only DTO a Slice exposes explicitly for cross-slice synchronous reads. A contract, not a model leak.</term>
        <term name="Domain Utility">A pure function or value type with zero side effects. Shared Kernel eligible only when it contains no slice-specific rules.</term>
        <term name="CONTEXT.md">Machine-readable contract file at each Slice root. The AI's cross-session memory for that Slice. Not documentation.</term>
    </terminology>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 2 — PROJECT CONTEXT
    All other sections are interpreted through these constraints.
    ================================================================ -->
    <project_context>
        <mode>solo-agent</mode>
        <backward_compatibility>disabled</backward_compatibility>

        <rule id="CTX-001" severity="blocker">
            No migration paths, compatibility shims, versioned endpoints, deprecated code paths, or adapter layers.
            If a better design exists, refactor completely.
        </rule>

        <rule id="CTX-002" severity="blocker" name="Atomic Full-Scope Execution">
            Large structural changes (DTO rename, slice split, file restructure, multi-slice refactor) MUST be
            executed completely and atomically in a single response. Partial execution leaving old and new
            patterns coexisting is FORBIDDEN.

            When a refactor affects two or more files, the AI MUST:
            1. Open the response with a numbered Execution Manifest listing every file to be created,
               modified, or deleted — with a one-line description of each change.
            2. Execute all items in the Manifest, in order, within the same response.
            3. Close with a Consistency Declaration: a brief summary confirming no stale references,
               no dangling imports, and no orphaned types remain.

            Exception — HARD GATE (pause required):
            Schema changes (new table, column addition/removal, renamed column, index change) MUST still
            follow the schema_confirmation gate defined in Section 3 before any implementation is written.
            All other changes proceed without interruption.

            Rationale: Modern agents operate with sufficient context capacity to deliver consistent
            multi-file changes in one pass. Step-by-step confirmation cycles impose coordination overhead
            without safety benefit for non-schema changes.
        </rule>

        <rule id="CTX-003" severity="high">
            No team-onboarding docs, contribution guides, or changelogs unless explicitly requested.
        </rule>

        <rule id="CTX-004" severity="high">
            Generated code must be production-grade. No scaffolding, no stubs, no "implement later" placeholders
            unless the developer explicitly requests a skeleton.
        </rule>
    </project_context>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 3 — AI HARD CONSTRAINTS
    Canonical rules live in the sections referenced. These entries are
    enforcement anchors: violations here are blocker-equivalent regardless
    of the severity declared in the canonical section.
    ================================================================ -->
    <ai_constraints>

        <!-- Architectural boundaries -->
        <never id="AC-001">Create Technical Slices (e.g., Slices/Authorization, Slices/EmailSender, Slices/Cache). These are Shared Kernel concerns.</never>
        <never id="AC-002">Allow any Slice to import, instantiate, or call the internal classes, handlers, repositories, or entities of another Slice. Only Public Read Models and Integration Events cross slice boundaries.</never>
        <never id="AC-006">Generate backward-compatible constructs: versioned interfaces, deprecated annotations, adapter wrappers, or migration-comment TODOs. → See CTX-001.</never>
        <never id="AC-008">Generate internal barrel/index files inside a Slice. Barrel files are permitted only at the Slice root to define its public export surface.</never>

        <!-- Code hygiene — canonical rules in Sections 7, 8, 9 -->
        <never id="AC-003">Generate commented-out code or dead code blocks. → See CM-002.</never>
        <never id="AC-004">Leave stub implementations unfinished (NotImplementedException, pass, todo!()) unless the developer explicitly requests a skeleton. → See CTX-004.</never>
        <never id="AC-005">Use generic file names: utils, helpers, common, misc, shared, base, manager, processor, or handler without a Feature prefix. → See Section 7 forbidden list.</never>
        <never id="AC-007">Write comments that describe WHAT the code does. Comments explain WHY only. → See CM-001.</never>

        <!-- Mandatory outputs -->
        <always id="AC-009">
            Require explicit, named Input and Output DTOs at every Slice entry point.
            Never return an internal domain model directly from an entry point.
            Exception: at Small scale (1–14 Slices, per Section 13), the Output DTO may be omitted
            when the DB entity shape exactly matches the required response shape and no transformation is needed.
        </always>
        <always id="AC-010">Validate input at the Slice boundary before it reaches the Handler. Validation is mandatory, not optional. → See Section 7, EP-VALIDATION.</always>
        <always id="AC-011">Update the affected Slice's CONTEXT.md in the same response as any interface, schema, or event change. Never let CONTEXT.md fall out of sync. → See Section 12.</always>
        <always id="AC-012">Apply guard clauses and early returns at the top of every function. Nested conditional depth beyond 2 MUST be refactored before delivery. → See CQ-001.</always>
        <always id="AC-013">Use named constants for every magic number, magic string, and configuration value. → See CM-004.</always>

        <schema_confirmation>
            Before generating any persistence schema, output the proposed schema as part of the Boundary Proposal.
            Do not proceed to implementation until the developer explicitly confirms in writing.
            Silence, absence of objection, or topic continuation is NOT approval.
        </schema_confirmation>
    </ai_constraints>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 4 — AI INTERACTION PROTOCOL
    ================================================================ -->
    <ai_interaction_protocol>

        <step sequence="1" name="Complexity Check">
            If fewer than 5 distinct business operations AND clearly a prototype or utility script,
            warn that VSA adds structural overhead. Proceed only on developer confirmation or
            if the project is already established as VSA.
        </step>

        <step sequence="2" name="Boundary Proposal">
            Before writing implementation code, output:
            (a) Slice name and its single business responsibility.
            (b) Full file/folder tree.
            (c) Input DTO, Output DTO, and Handler signature.
            (d) Persistence schema if applicable (triggers schema_confirmation).
            Infer from context first. Ask ONE clarifying question only if a boundary is genuinely ambiguous after inference.
        </step>

        <step sequence="3" name="Completeness Check">
            After generating a Slice, verify all mandatory components exist:
            Entry Point, Input Model, Validator, Handler, CONTEXT.md.
            Generate any missing component before ending the response.
        </step>

        <step sequence="4" name="Consistency Scan">
            After any change, report:
            - Other Slices affected by the interface or schema change.
            - Stale CONTEXT.md files referencing the modified surface.
            - Shared Kernel utilities that may have absorbed business logic.
            Do not silently leave inconsistencies.
        </step>
    </ai_interaction_protocol>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 5 — CORE PRINCIPLES
    ================================================================ -->
    <core_principles>

        <principle name="Cohesion over DRY">
            <rule>
                Always duplicate business logic across Slices.
                Do NOT create a shared module based on the AI's prediction of future divergence —
                LLMs cannot reliably predict domain evolution.
                Business logic moves to the Shared Kernel as a Domain Utility ONLY when the developer
                issues the explicit command: /abstract [LogicName]
                Without that command, duplication is the default and correct action.
                Never create a CommonBusiness or SharedLogic module.
            </rule>
            <exception id="PURE-FN-EXCEPTION">
                Pure functions with zero side effects representing a universal domain concept
                (e.g., Money arithmetic, VAT calculation, slug generation) are Shared Kernel eligible
                from initial creation WITHOUT requiring an /abstract command.
                A function qualifies only when: (a) it has zero side effects, (b) it contains no
                branch logic tied to any specific Slice's business rules, and (c) it is genuinely
                universal — applicable identically across any Slice that might use it.
            </exception>
        </principle>

        <principle name="Slice Independence">
            <rule>
                Deleting a Slice folder plus its DI registration and event subscriptions
                must leave the project in a compilable, fully functional state.
                If deletion requires modifying code inside another Slice, the boundaries are wrong.
            </rule>
        </principle>

        <principle name="Transactional Integrity">
            <rule>
                One Slice = One Transaction. Never coordinate DB transactions across Slice boundaries.
                Multi-slice state changes use the Saga pattern via Integration Events.
            </rule>
        </principle>

        <principle name="Error Handling">
            <rule>
                Slices MUST NOT use exceptions for business flow control.
                Return a Result/Either type from Handler to Entry Point.
                Exceptions are reserved for unexpected infrastructure failures only.
            </rule>
        </principle>

        <principle name="Single Responsibility per Slice">
            <rule>
                A Slice performs exactly one primary business action.
                If the Slice name requires the word "and," split it.
                The business action must be expressible in one imperative sentence without conjunctions.
            </rule>
        </principle>

        <principle name="No Speculative Generality">
            <rule>
                Do not generate abstractions, interfaces, or extension points for capabilities that do not yet exist.
                Build for the current requirement. Introduce extensibility at the moment it is needed.
            </rule>
        </principle>
    </core_principles>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 6 — SLICE ANATOMY
    ================================================================ -->
    <slice_anatomy>
        <mandatory>
            <component role="Entry Point">Routes, HTTP binding, Entry Point → Handler call, Result → protocol response. Zero business logic.</component>
            <component role="Input Model">Immutable DTO/Command/Query. Named [Feature]Command or [Feature]Query.</component>
            <component role="Validator">Enforces all invariants checkable without a DB call. DB checks (uniqueness, existence) belong in the Handler.</component>
            <component role="Handler">Single class. Orchestrates domain logic, persistence, event publishing. The only business logic location.</component>
            <component role="CONTEXT.md">Machine-readable contract. Updated on every interface or schema change. See Section 12.</component>
        </mandatory>
        <optional>
            <component role="Domain Model">Required only when the Slice has complex encapsulated invariants. Omit for simple CRUD.</component>
            <component role="Repository">Required when the Handler has more than one DB operation or a non-trivial query. Small scale: inline persistence in Handler is permitted.</component>
            <component role="Output Model">Named [Feature]Response. Required when response shape differs from the DB entity. At Small scale, may be omitted when shapes match exactly — see AC-009.</component>
            <component role="Projection">Required only for cross-slice synchronous reads. Exposes slice data without leaking internal models.</component>
        </optional>
    </slice_anatomy>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 7 — FILE NAMING CONVENTIONS
    ================================================================ -->
    <file_naming_conventions>

        <convention id="FN-001">
            Pattern: [FeatureName].[Role].[ext]
            FeatureName = PascalCase business capability (PlaceOrder, RegisterUser, GenerateInvoice).
            Role = drawn exclusively from the Role Vocabulary below.
        </convention>

        <role_vocabulary>
            <role name="Handler">The UseCase/Handler class. One per Slice.</role>
            <role name="Command">A mutating Input DTO.</role>
            <role name="Query">A read-only Input DTO.</role>
            <role name="Validator">Input validation logic.</role>
            <role name="Repository">Data access abstraction.</role>
            <role name="Response">Output DTO returned from the entry point.</role>
            <role name="Endpoint">Entry point: controller, route, or consumer.</role>
            <role name="Model">Domain or persistence model internal to the Slice.</role>
            <role name="Event">Integration event emitted by the Slice.</role>
            <role name="Projection">Public Read Model for cross-slice reads.</role>
            <role name="DomainService">Complex domain logic with zero infrastructure dependencies.</role>
        </role_vocabulary>

        <convention id="FN-002">
            Test files: [FeatureName].[Role].Test.[ext]
            Co-located in a /tests subfolder within the Feature Folder.
            Example: PlaceOrder.Handler.Test.ts
        </convention>

        <convention id="FN-003">
            Shared Kernel files: [ConceptName].[Role].[ext]
            ConceptName is a domain concept, never a technical descriptor.
            Examples: Money.ValueObject.ts | Logger.Adapter.ts | DatabaseConnection.Config.ts
        </convention>

        <forbidden>utils | helpers | common | misc | shared | manager | processor | base (without feature prefix) | index (except Slice public barrel)</forbidden>
    </file_naming_conventions>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 8 — COMMENT POLICY
    ================================================================ -->
    <comment_policy>

        <rule id="CM-001" severity="high">
            Comments explain WHY, never WHAT.
            WRONG: // Loop through orders and sum the totals
            RIGHT: // Summed here rather than in the DB query because tax calculation requires hydrated domain objects.
        </rule>

        <rule id="CM-002" severity="blocker">
            Dead code MUST be deleted, never commented out. Use version control for history.
        </rule>

        <rule id="CM-003" severity="high">
            TODO comments MUST include reason and context.
            WRONG: // TODO: fix this
            RIGHT: // TODO: Replace with event-driven approach once the Notification slice is implemented.
        </rule>

        <rule id="CM-004" severity="medium">
            Replace magic numbers and non-obvious strings with named constants.
            If the constant name is not self-explanatory, add a WHY comment at the declaration — not at the usage site.
            WRONG: const timeout = 30000; // 30 second timeout
            RIGHT: const SESSION_EXPIRY_MS = 30_000; // Matches the upstream auth provider's token TTL.
        </rule>

        <rule id="CM-005" severity="medium">
            Auto-generated doc comments that restate the function or parameter name are FORBIDDEN.
            Exception: public API surface methods with non-obvious behavior or constraints.
        </rule>

        <rule id="CM-006" severity="low">
            Section divider comments (// ===== INIT =====) are FORBIDDEN.
            A file requiring dividers to be navigable violates single responsibility. Split it.
        </rule>

        <rule id="CM-007" severity="high">
            Non-obvious business rules embedded in code MUST have a WHY comment explaining the business constraint.
            Example: // Orders under €10 ineligible per carrier contract FUL-2024-03.
        </rule>
    </comment_policy>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 9 — CODE QUALITY CONSTRAINTS
    ================================================================ -->
    <code_quality_constraints>

        <rule id="CQ-001" severity="high">Guard clauses and early returns at the top of every function. Happy path = least indented path. Depth &gt; 2 MUST be refactored before delivery.</rule>
        <rule id="CQ-002" severity="high">No unused imports, unused variables, unused parameters, or unreachable code in any generated output.</rule>
        <rule id="CQ-003" severity="medium">Single nameable responsibility per function. Prefer extraction when a method exceeds 60 lines.</rule>
        <rule id="CQ-004" severity="high">Boolean parameters that alter execution path are FORBIDDEN. Use separate explicitly named functions. WRONG: processOrder(order, isDraft: true) RIGHT: saveDraftOrder(order) | submitOrder(order)</rule>
        <rule id="CQ-005" severity="medium">Nested ternaries limited to depth 1. Complex conditional assignment uses if/else or a lookup structure.</rule>
        <rule id="CQ-006" severity="medium">No generic abstractions, base classes, or factory patterns for a single concrete implementation. Abstract only when two or more concrete implementations exist.</rule>
        <rule id="CQ-007" severity="low">Prefer explicit over implicit. Avoid clever one-liners that sacrifice readability for brevity.</rule>
        <rule id="CQ-008" severity="medium">Config files include only actively used keys. No commented-out configuration options as reference.</rule>
    </code_quality_constraints>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 10 — DATA SOVEREIGNTY
    ================================================================ -->
    <data_sovereignty_rules>

        <rule id="DS-001" severity="blocker">A Slice MUST own its tables/collections exclusively. Only the owning Slice may write to them.</rule>
        <rule id="DS-002" severity="blocker">No SQL JOINs, subqueries, or cross-collection aggregations between tables owned by different Slices.</rule>
        <rule id="DS-003" severity="critical">
            Cross-slice data sync:
            (a) Mutations: async via Integration Events only.
            (b) Reads: sync via an explicitly defined Public Read Model only. Never reference the owning Slice's internal DTO, entity, or repository.
        </rule>
        <rule id="DS-004" severity="high">Shared database table naming: [slicename]_[tablename] (lowercase snake_case). Example: ordering_lines, catalog_products.</rule>
        <rule id="DS-005" severity="high">Integration Event schemas are immutable once published. Schema changes require a new event type. This is the only permitted deprecation scenario in this ruleset.</rule>
    </data_sovereignty_rules>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 11 — REFACTORING TRIGGERS
    When any trigger fires: HALT, report the trigger ID,
    propose a concrete fix, wait for explicit confirmation before continuing.
    ================================================================ -->
    <refactoring_triggers>

        <trigger id="RT-001" severity="blocker">
            <condition>Handler/UseCase exceeds 300 lines OR has more than 5 injected dependencies.</condition>
            <action>
                Flag the trigger inline. Identify sub-operations. Output the proposed split as a named
                Command list at the top of the response, then execute the full split atomically in the same
                response per CTX-002. Do NOT halt for confirmation unless a schema change is involved.
            </action>
        </trigger>

        <trigger id="RT-002" severity="high">
            <condition>CONTEXT.md Purpose requires "and" to describe the Slice's responsibility, or describes two distinct outcomes.</condition>
            <action>
                Flag the trigger inline. Output CONTEXT.md outlines for both proposed Slices at the top of the
                response, then execute the full split atomically per CTX-002.
                If the correct boundary is genuinely ambiguous after inference, ask ONE targeted question before proceeding.
            </action>
        </trigger>

        <trigger id="RT-003" severity="high">
            <condition>A Shared Kernel utility contains conditional logic tied to a specific business scenario.</condition>
            <action>
                Flag as God Utility inline. Move the business branch into the relevant Slice atomically in the same
                response. The Shared Kernel function must be left pure upon completion.
            </action>
        </trigger>

        <trigger id="RT-004" severity="high">
            <condition>A Slice imports more than one other Slice's Public Read Model OR subscribes to more than three Integration Events.</condition>
            <action>
                Flag boundary misalignment inline. State the proposed resolution (Read Model replication or boundary
                redraw) and execute the correction atomically in the same response per CTX-002.
            </action>
        </trigger>

        <trigger id="RT-005" severity="medium">
            <condition>Identical validation logic duplicated across three or more Slices.</condition>
            <action>
                Flag the duplication inline with a WHY comment and the names of the affected Slices.
                Do NOT abstract automatically. Abstraction requires an explicit developer command: /abstract [ValidatorName]
                This gate is intentional and consistent with the Cohesion over DRY principle (Section 5).
                Upon receiving /abstract [ValidatorName], execute the move atomically per CTX-002.
            </action>
        </trigger>
    </refactoring_triggers>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 12 — LIVING CONTEXT DOCUMENTATION (CONTEXT.md)
    ================================================================ -->
    <living_documentation>
        <rule>Every Slice MUST have a CONTEXT.md. It is a mandatory Slice component.</rule>
        <rule>
            Update CONTEXT.md in the SAME response as any change to:
            Input/Output DTO | DB table or collection | Published or consumed event |
            Slice name, Handler name, or Entry Point | Shared Kernel dependency.
        </rule>

        <template>
            <![CDATA[
            # [SliceName]

            ## Purpose
            [One sentence. The single business action this slice performs.]

            ## Entry Point
            - Type: [HTTP POST | HTTP GET | Event Consumer | CLI | ...]
            - Input: `[CommandName | QueryName]`
            - Output: `[ResponseName | void]`

            ## Data Ownership
            - Tables: `[slicename_tablename]`
            - Events Published: `[EventName]` (omit if none)
            - Events Consumed: `[EventName]` (omit if none)
            - Public Read Model: `[ProjectionName]` (omit if none)

            ## Shared Kernel
            - [UtilityName] — [why] (omit section if none)

            ## Notes
            [Non-obvious design decisions or constraints only. Omit for straightforward slices.]
            ]]>
        </template>
    </living_documentation>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 13 — CONTEXT SCALING
    ================================================================ -->
    <context_scaling>

        <scale level="Small" criteria="1–14 Slices">
            <permitted>DB entities used directly in Handlers. No Repository required.</permitted>
            <permitted>Single shared DbContext or DB connection.</permitted>
            <permitted>In-memory event bus.</permitted>
            <permitted>Output Model omitted when the DB entity shape exactly matches the required response and no transformation is needed. See AC-009 for the full rule.</permitted>
            <required>All AC, DS, FN, CM, CQ rules apply without exception.</required>
            <required>Input validation is always mandatory.</required>
        </scale>

        <scale level="Medium" criteria="15–40 Slices">
            <required>Strict DTO separation: Input Model, Output Model, and DB Entity are distinct types.</required>
            <required>Repository or Query Object for all non-trivial persistence.</required>
            <required>Slice-specific DbContext or namespace-isolated collection.</required>
            <required>Full CONTEXT.md template.</required>
        </scale>

        <scale level="Large" criteria="41+ Slices">
            <required>All Medium requirements.</required>
            <required>Dedicated DbContext per Slice with no shared entity registration.</required>
            <required>Outbox Pattern for all Integration Events.</required>
            <required>Explicit Projection types for all cross-slice reads.</required>
            <required>Architecture test suite enforcing no-cross-slice-reference rule. Generated once per project setup, not per Slice.</required>
        </scale>
    </context_scaling>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 14 — CONFLICT RESOLUTION
    ================================================================ -->
    <conflict_resolution>

        <scenario name="Shared Business Logic">
            <condition>Business logic used in two or more Slices.</condition>
            <action>
                Duplicate by default.
                Move to Shared Kernel ONLY on explicit /abstract [LogicName] command from the developer.
                Exception: pure functions with zero side effects representing a universal domain concept
                (e.g., Money arithmetic, VAT calculation, slug generation) may be placed in the Shared Kernel
                from initial creation without an /abstract command, provided they meet all criteria of
                the PURE-FN-EXCEPTION defined in Section 5.
            </action>
        </scenario>

        <scenario name="Shared Infrastructure Logic">
            <condition>Purely technical logic: logging, email transport, DB connection, HTTP client.</condition>
            <action>Move to Shared Kernel. Implementation must be a generic adapter with zero awareness of any specific Slice.</action>
        </scenario>

        <scenario name="Cross-Slice Read">
            <condition>Slice A needs data owned by Slice B to compose a response.</condition>
            <action>Option 1 (infrequent reads): Gateway Aggregator at the entry point layer. Option 2 (frequent reads): Slice A maintains a Read Model replica kept in sync via Integration Events. FORBIDDEN: calling Slice B's repository, handler, or entity directly.</action>
        </scenario>

        <scenario name="Ambiguous Slice Ownership">
            <condition>A new feature could belong to two existing Slices.</condition>
            <action>Identify which existing Slice's single responsibility would change. That Slice is the owner. If both would change, create a new Slice.</action>
        </scenario>
    </conflict_resolution>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 15 — TESTING
    ================================================================ -->
    <testing_standards>
        <rule id="TS-001" severity="high">
            Generate tests ONLY when the developer appends --test to the prompt.
            Without --test, generate no test files.
        </rule>

        <rule id="TS-002" severity="high">
            When --test is present, generate one Integration Test covering the full Slice
            from entry point through Handler to the real or in-memory database.
            The test MUST assert on actual system state after execution
            (record persisted, event published) — not only the return value.
            Test file: [FeatureName].Integration.Test.[ext], co-located in /tests within the Feature Folder.
        </rule>

        <rule id="TS-003" severity="medium">
            Exception: if the Slice Handler contains complex branching or non-trivial domain calculations,
            also generate a targeted Unit Test for that logic in isolation.
            Mock only infrastructure boundaries (repository, event bus, external services).
            Do NOT mock domain services or value objects.
            Test file: [FeatureName].Handler.Test.[ext]
        </rule>
    </testing_standards>


    <!-- ================================================================
    SECTION 16 — EXTENSION POINTS
    Child configs MUST inherit this file and implement all mandatory
    points. Child configs MUST NOT contradict any rule above.
    ================================================================ -->
    <extension_points>
        <instruction>Child configurations MUST declare which extension points they implement.</instruction>

        <point id="EP-PROJECT-STRUCTURE"  mandatory="true"  contract="Concrete folder layout implementing [Feature]/[Feature].[Role].[ext]. Full Feature Folder template with all mandatory components."/>
        <point id="EP-FILE-NAMING"        mandatory="true"  contract="Language casing rules (PascalCase|snake_case|kebab-case). Role Vocabulary mapped to idiomatic language names."/>
        <point id="EP-ENDPOINT"           mandatory="true"  contract="Concrete Entry Point syntax: Minimal API | Controller | Route Handler | gRPC | GraphQL | CLI | Message Consumer."/>
        <point id="EP-HANDLER"            mandatory="true"  contract="Concrete Handler pattern with Result/Either return type implementation."/>
        <point id="EP-VALIDATION"         mandatory="true"  contract="Concrete validation wired at Slice boundary before Handler. Must show pipeline integration."/>
        <point id="EP-RESULT-TYPE"        mandatory="true"  contract="Concrete Result/Either implementation replacing exceptions for all business outcomes."/>
        <point id="EP-PERSISTENCE"        mandatory="true"  contract="Persistence pattern per scale: Small (inline) | Medium (Repository) | Large (Slice DbContext). Table naming convention implementation."/>
        <point id="EP-DI-REGISTRATION"    mandatory="true"  contract="Slice self-registration supporting delete-folder-remove-registration compile test."/>
        <point id="EP-TESTING"            mandatory="true"  contract="Integration test setup (real/in-memory DB). Confirm test file co-location in Feature Folder."/>
        <point id="EP-EVENT-BUS"          mandatory="false" contract="Event bus per scale: Small (in-memory) | Medium (in-process persistent) | Large (Outbox + external broker)."/>
        <point id="EP-ARCH-TESTS"         mandatory="false" contract="Automated no-cross-slice-reference enforcement. Mandatory at Large scale (41+ Slices)."/>
        <point id="EP-CONTEXT-TEMPLATE"   mandatory="false" contract="Language-specific CONTEXT.md additions (e.g., migration file names, package references). Must not contradict base template."/>
    </extension_points>

</vertical_slice_guidelines>
